<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Avoiding Exposition</title>
    <description>I&#39;m a PhD Candidate in the School of Computer Science at Univeristy of Manchester. I study scientists behaviour towards Data Sharing and Collaboration.
</description>
    <link>http://kjgarza.github.io/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://kjgarza.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <pubDate>Sun, 17 Apr 2016 23:42:09 +0100</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 17 Apr 2016 23:42:09 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v2.4.0</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Merge RQDA and Annotations to make the killer app</title>
        <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;There is not a perfect #CAQDAS but #RQDA and #Annotations are leading the way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://i.imgur.com/LSv0PEm.png = 20x&quot; alt=&quot;Coding Interviews&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the experiences I loathe during my research was coding interview transcripts. The process was confusing, mechanical, and required a good deal of organisation for which I was not ready. I tend to throw technical solutions at problems and so I did with this one. I used the CAQDAS application RQDA&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:rqda&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:rqda&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. RQDA is an R package with a GUI that can be used to analyse textual data.  Unfortunately, my CAQDAS selection turned out to be not a great decision but not because RQDA was not perfect but because currently there is no perfect CAQDAS solution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wish I had been more analytical on the tool selection and checked a few options. Because, unfortunately, reviews are not great source of help, as they mostly list the features of each CAQDAS solution (e.g. Woods, Macklin, and Lewis 2015&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:woods&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:woods&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, Schönfelder 2011&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:scho&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:scho&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, Hwang 2008&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:hwang&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:hwang&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, Lewins and Silver 2009&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:lewis&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:lewis&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;). If I could have something different I would have taken a few of these CAQDAS solutions used for a bit and compared them. That is what I have retrospectively made in this post. I took three CAQDAS solutions (i.e. &lt;a href=&quot;http://rqda.r-forge.r-project.org/&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;RQDA&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.annotationsapp.com/&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Annotations&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/a&gt;and &lt;a href=&quot;http://atlasti.com/&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Atlas.ti&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;) and compared them in four simple aspects: Coding Experience, Coding Exporting, Analysis Tools and Inter-coder Reliability Support. The results are in the table below:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;    &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table rules=&quot;groups&quot;&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Solution&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Coding Experience&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Coding Exporting&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Analysis Tools&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Inter-coder Reliability Support&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;License&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;RQDA&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;CT:  7.5sec           CC: 13.42sec&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;em&gt;2&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;em&gt;Multitude of packages&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;em&gt;Multiple coders&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Free&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Atlas.ti&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;CT:  6.82sec            CC: 7.10sec&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Word Crucher and Concurrency Table&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Multiple coders&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Proprietary&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Annotations&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;CT:  &lt;em&gt;5.1sec&lt;/em&gt;             CC:  &lt;em&gt;6.99sec&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;No support&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;No support&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Proprietary&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
  &lt;tfoot&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tfoot&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Time is   given in seconds
&lt;strong&gt;CT&lt;/strong&gt;: Time   to code/tag text
&lt;strong&gt;CC&lt;/strong&gt;: Time   to create a new code/tag&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In terms of coding experience, Annotations is the best and fastest coding experience. Atlas.ti comes close but Annotations is still a bit ahead in terms of speed. This could be mostly related to Annotation’s auto pop-up tagging menu, which appears every time you select a piece of text. RQDA trails way behind the other two solutions mostly due to the lack of autocomplete search for codes; a feature both Atlas.ti and Annotations have built-in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, RQDA offer advantages in other dimensions. The backend of Annotations and to some extend Atlas.ti are in shambles when compared with RQDA. RQDA can handle almost any standard data exchange format &lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:formats&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:formats&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; , which comes very useful to exchange your coded text with other applications, R scripts, or even publishing your data. Atlas.ti at least can output the coded text in XML but Annotations can only expert plain text on HTML.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In terms of analysis tools, RQDA has a number of tools included in the package like a code concurrency table; but it can be hooked up with many other R libraries to conduct Sentiment Analysis, Text Mining, Visualisation, etc &lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:rpack&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:rpack&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. Atlas.ti also supports a concurrency table and a word cruncher. On the other hand, Annotations no analysis tools. The lack of analysis tools could stem from the perspective that doing a quantitative analysis in qualitative data does not lead to reliable inferences. In essence, RQDA’s backend robustness is superior to the other two solutions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A worrying issue is the absence of support of Intercode reliability in all these packages. RQDA and Atlas.ti both support multiple coders but no tool is provided to check reliability among them. The lack of support in this area could be related to the same reason as with the lack of analysis tools (i.e., quantitative analysis in qualitative data.). If that is the case, then the software should support other types of analysis tools. For example, support card sorting as a reliability test &lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:cards&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:cards&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall, &lt;strong&gt;Atlas.ti&lt;/strong&gt; seems a decent compromise between the usability and speed of &lt;strong&gt;Annotations&lt;/strong&gt; and the backend of &lt;strong&gt;RQDA&lt;/strong&gt;. Unfortunately, Atlas.ti is not free or open. I think that to make the killer app you will need a combination of the Annotations front-end with the RQDA backend. This would certainly would disrupt the entire CAQDAS market, because using RQDA would mean that the app has to be open. I can only wish that Christian Klutz (Annotations) and Huang Ronggui (RQDA) would sit together and make this happen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p style=&quot;background-color:white; font-size: 80%; text-align: justify;&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Methods&lt;/strong&gt;
I compared the three solutions in four areas: Coding Experience, Coding Exporting, Analysis Tools and Inter-coder Reliability Support. First, I use the term coding experience to refer the usability of the software to code text and create codes (i.e., tags). I used the Keystroke-level (KL) model to quantify coding experience. The KL model predicts how long it will take an expert user to accomplish a routine task without errors &lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:klm&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:klm&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;9&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; . Second, I use the term Coding Exporting to refer to the options to export the coded/tagged text into other formats or applications. I ranked each application’s exporting capabilities based on whether or not they could export in to a Web/ISO standard exchange format and whether the exporting language was available in a computer interpretable form &lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:formats:1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:formats&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. Third, Analysis tools refer to the availability of tools for coded text. Specifically, whether the tools a quantitative tools and how many analysis they can be performed. Fourth, I used the term Intercoder Reliability Support to refer features the application provide to support two or more independent coders to evaluate the same data/text.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:rqda&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;HUANG Ronggui (2014). RQDA: R-based Qualitative Data Analysis. R package version 0.2-7. http://rqda.r-forge.r-project.org/ &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:rqda&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:woods&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Woods, Megan, Rob Macklin, and Gemma K. Lewis. 2015. “Researcher Reflexivity: Exploring the Impacts of CAQDAS Use.” International Journal of Social Research Methodology 0 (0): 1–19. doi:10.1080/13645579.2015.1023964. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:woods&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:scho&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Schönfelder, Walter. 2011. “CAQDAS and Qualitative Syllogism Logic—NVivo 8 and MAXQDA 10 Compared.” Forum Qualitative Sozialforschung / Forum: Qualitative Social Research 12 (1). http://www.qualitative-research.net/index.php/fqs/article/view/1514. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:scho&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:hwang&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Hwang, Sungsoo. 2008. “Utilizing Qualitative Data Analysis Software: A Review of Atlas.ti.” Social Science Computer Review, February. doi:10.1177/0894439307312485. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:hwang&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:lewis&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Lewins, Ann, and Christina Silver. 2009. “Choosing a CAQDAS Package.” Working Paper. Guildford, UK: University of Surrey. http://caqdas.soc.surrey.ac.uk/PDF/2009ChoosingaCAQDASPackage.pdf. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:lewis&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:formats&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Data_exchange &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:formats&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:formats:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:rpack&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;http://rpackages.ianhowson.com/all/ &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:rpack&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:cards&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Stephen C. Bowden , Kylie S. Fowler , Richard C. Bell , Gregory Whelan ,Christine C. Clifford , Alison J. Ritter &amp;amp; Caroline M. Long (1998) The Reliability and Internal Validity of the Wisconsin Card Sorting Test, Neuropsychological Rehabilitation, 8:3, 243-254, DOI: 10.1080/713755573 &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:cards&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:klm&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;http://courses.csail.mit.edu/6.831/2009/handouts/ac18-predictive-evaluation/klm.shtml &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:klm&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 31 Mar 2016 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://kjgarza.github.io/pages/2016/03/31/Killer-CAQDAS-Solution.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://kjgarza.github.io/pages/2016/03/31/Killer-CAQDAS-Solution.html</guid>
        
        <category>review</category>
        
        <category>CAQDAS</category>
        
        <category>RQDA</category>
        
        <category>Annotations</category>
        
        
        <category>pages</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>A mucho vino poco tino</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;El hombre miró al piso antes de caer fulminado.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dos horas antes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Voy a matarlo. Voy a matarte, Gilberto G. -me repito mientras entro al hotel.  Libro la vigilancia del área de servicio diciendo que soy del equipo de meseros. A paso firme me dirijo a los vestidores mientras oculto mi mirada de todos los que me rodean. Siento como si tuviera cargando a alguien en mis hombros. Mi cuello está tenso y mi columna tiembla. Sin embargo, estoy tan concentrado que ni siquiera puedo escuchar el va y viene de la gente del hotel mientras camino por los pasillos de servicio.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pido un uniforme limpio, y me apresuro a colocármelo. Con el cuidado con el que se maneja un bebé, paso el veneno del bolsillo de mi chamarra a los pantalones del uniforme. Ninguno de los otros meseros parece notar mi inusual presencia, quizás porque el turno está a punto de terminar y están todos cansados.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Me dirijo al bar en la planta baja del hotel y ordeno una copa de vino, dando el número del primer cuarto que me viene a la mente. No puedo separar la mirada de las manos del cantinero mientras sirve el vino. Dejo que coloque la copa en mi charola, y apresuradamente me doy media vuelta sin decir nada. Antes de alejarme lo oigo balbucear algo, pero no puedo distinguir qué dijo, y no me importa.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;De pronto, siento mi brazo ser tomado con firmeza. Mi corazón se acelera. Es uno de los supervisores.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;-Tienes otro pedido- me dice apuntando en la dirección del cantinero.
-¿Vas al primer piso, cierto? Lleva esta copa a la oficina de Gilberto G. –me ordena el cantinero mientras pone otra copa en mi charola.- ¿Sabes dónde está?
Yo solo contesto con la cabeza.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Me apresuro a vertir el veneno en una de las copas de vino mientras estoy en el elevador. Dejo momentáneamente la copa extra en el piso para después regresarla a la charola y colocar veneno en ella también. Será menos sospechoso si le doy a elegir, pienso.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sin darme cuenta ya estoy enfrente de la puerta de Gilberto G. La golpeo dos veces como me enseñaron durante la inducción semanas antes, pero ante la nula respuesta me aventuro a abrirla.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;-Pasa, pasa, déjalo sobre la mesa. Me sorprende el mismo Gilberto, quien se encuentra en su escritorio. No parece recordar mi rostro. Aunque tampoco me dirige la mirada. Coloco la charola sobre la mesa mientras él se levanta, y se dirige hacia mí, manteniendo su mirada en un par de documentos que sostiene a la altura del pecho.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Como con el cantinero, mi mirada está fija de nuevo sobre la copa de vino. Ahora solo estoy esperando que la tome para salir de la oficina.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mi cuerpo se sacude de terror cuando escucho la puerta abrirse con brusquedad. Un hombre entra, pero se detiene intempestivamente al verme. Déjanos solos, me ordena mientras sostiene la puerta para que yo salga. Yo obedezco sin ni siquiera pensar.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Me quedo afuera de la oficina sin saber qué hacer. Debería de irme o debería esperar, me pregunto. Puedo escuchar sus voces, pero no puedo distinguir si están riendo o gritando.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Decido irme.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Entro al elevador y presiono el botón del lobby. Pero antes de que se cierren las puertas veo al hombre salir de la oficina de Gilberto G.  Sin saber por qué detengo las puertas del elevador. Acto seguido el hombre miró al piso…&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 07 Sep 2013 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://kjgarza.github.io/pages/2013/09/07/short-story-wine.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://kjgarza.github.io/pages/2013/09/07/short-story-wine.html</guid>
        
        <category>short-story</category>
        
        <category>nonlinear</category>
        
        
        <category>pages</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>How can Social Semantic Web Enable Collective Intelligence and improve Knowledge Discovery Strategies in a Heliophysics Virtual Observatory</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Kristian Garza&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;kj.garza@gmail.com&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;introduction&quot;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Heliophysics is an environmental science that analyses the connections between the Sun, solar wind, planetary space environments, and our place in the Galaxy, in an attempt to uncover the fundamental physical processes that occur throughout the Universe  (NASA, 2011). Heliophysics has experienced an exponential growth in the amount and variety of data collected. The community has responded to this challenge with the development of Virtual Heliophysics Observatories linking databases from all over the world  (Martens, 2010). Although Virtual Observatories (VxOs) efficiently link data from many research centres, they are mostly used to overcome infrastructure barriers. Most of their services are domain-specific and their data models do not value links created by user interaction with the data objects in the Virtual Observatory (i.e. has data-set A been analysed with program D? Who has published something about data-set A? Who is analysing data-set A or an ontologically related data-set?) .  At the same time, research has been conducted, which holds the view that to achieve the potential of e-Science implementations; the social aspect of research must be taken into consideration. This proposal seeks to discover the principles under which Social Networking and Semantic Web Technology can improve Knowledge Discovery strategies in a Virtual Organisation for the Heliophysics community. Specifically, I use an ontology to annotate the user’s activities and groundwork within the Virtual Observatory to expose them to other users, who might be interested. I intend to develop this work on top of the Heliophysics Integrated Observatory (HELIO)&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This work seeks to uncover and find a way to overcome the challenges for Social Semantic Web within Virtual Observatories to aid the research of Heliophysics. It particularly, seeks to define a service architecture for Social Semantic Web Services that would enable Collective Intelligence, efficiently leverage knowledge discovery and manage expertise. The hypothesis that semantically targeting user behaviour and interactions with data objects can improve knowledge discovery strategies in a Virtual Observatory will be tested. It will set out to answer how socially embedded applications based on semantic web technology impact the research activities of users in a Virtual Observatory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite the fact that Virtual Observatories have considered using Semantic Web technology in the past, only recently has this formally been attempted. The field of Heliophysics presents both challenges and opportunities for the Semantic Web and the Virtual Observatory. Combining data from five fields of physical science (Solar, Heliospheric, Planetary, Iono/Magnetospheric and Astronomical data) including 43 space missions, around 153 instruments each with many own data products, the Heliophysics Integrated Observatory represents a challenge in data heterogeneity. HELIO will associate data from observations in all above-mentioned fields of science for the first time  (Bentley, 2009). Being attentive to this development opens the opportunity to link this cloud of data with many more other related objects on the World Wide Web. Such objects include publications, algorithms, patents and workflows.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main goal of this research is to develop a foundation for Social Semantic Web tools in other Virtual Observatories as a means of improving knowledge discovery, as well as assess the advantages and disadvantages of this approach to enable Collective Intelligence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On a wider note, tracking data user interaction and targeting it to other users within an e-infrastructure such as HELIO, may well trigger knowledge discovery in a more serendipitous fashion.
Literature Review&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The concept of The Virtual Observatory (VxO) has been described as the astronomy community’s response to the challenge of analysing and processing astronomical data sets (Djorgovski &amp;amp; Williams, 2005), (Lawrence, 2002), (Quin, 2003). These data sets are growing in volume and complexity at staggering speed . In principle, VxOs are openly distributed research environments that provide astronomers with massive and complex data sets. It assembles data archives and services, as well as data exploration and analysis tools.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Djorgovski states  (Djorgovski &amp;amp; Williams, 2005) that a Virtual Observatory follows two main discovery strategies. Firstly, covering a large volume of parametric space. Secondly, by connecting as many different types of observations as possible so as to increase the potential of discovery as a function of the number of connections.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Early Virtual Observatory implementations use the architecture defined by The International Virtual Observatory Alliance (IVOA) in  (Williams, 2004). The IVOA architecture has successfully provided transparent access to databases and repositories around the world. For instance, the National Virtual Observatory maps databases from hundreds of research centres for the Astronomy Community, and AstroGrid connects most of UK’s scientific data centres  (AstroGrid Team, 2001).  The IVOA Knowledge Discovery in Databases Interest Group (KDD-IG) defines in  (Longo, 2011) the use of data mining as an effort to enrich their Knowledge Discovery strategy. This approach seeks to discover patterns, associations, changes, anomalies, and statistically significant structures and events in data in a semi-automatic manner. Some examples of this approach are the DAME project  (Brescia et al., 2010) and the AMDA project (Genot et al., 2010).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In  (Borne, 2003) Borne presents four directions users can take to carry out data mining in a Virtual Observatory. Two of these directions are Known Events/Known Algorithms and Known Events/Unknown Algorithms and they require users to input models from known phenomena in order to drive data mining.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One recent VxO implementation uses Semantic Web Technology to improve the efficiency and interoperability in comparison with traditional architectures. In (Fox et al., 2009), Peter Fox proposes architecture based on ontology, whose primary objective is to connect as many different types of observation as possible.  In  (Fox et al., 2007), Fox indicates that scientists have a liking for the partial exposure of the ontology in a Virtual Observatory. Primarily because this exposure gives them some insight about the data they are retrieving. I believe this contributes to the Knowledge Discovery strategy of this implementation. Fox also argues  (Fox et al., 2007) that Semantic Web could realize the VxO potential in the areas of collaborative research, and impact of a wide range of interdisciplinary scientific research.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Current Virtual Observatory implementations do not completely fulfil the objectives of the second discovery strategy by not including the users’ interactions with the VxO objects (data). Although VxOs implementations are evolving their knowledge discovery strategies with the use of pattern recognition and data mining, the need for identifying phenomena before using this technology opens the door for other approaches. At the same time, in the VxO interoperability with the WWW is still a pending issue, and using users’ information to provide that link could very well help to close that loop.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In  (Roure, 2008) De Roure argues that to facilitate the discovery and interpretation of knowledge it is necessary to develop technologies that assist collaboration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Adding a Social Facet to the VxO would augment its knowledge discovery strategy by increasing the amount of useful connections significantly. The Virtual Observatory already deals with object of social interest for the scientific community: scientific data. These objects are rich in meta-data and in a Semantic Web Virtual Observatory they also have a high degree of interoperability. However, scientists add other types of meta-data when they retrieve, analyse, or process these data objects. This meta-data can provide scientists with insight about the events they are analysing. This meta-data could answer questions such as: Who has been consulting these data? What applications have other users implemented­­ to analyse these data?, Who has published something based on these data?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An example of this data notation is the Science Collaboration Framework platform (Das et al., 2009), which allows scientists to attach scientific discourse to publications. In this framework ontologies, such as  the Semantic Web Applications in Neuromedicine (SWAN) Ontology (Ciccarese et al., 2008), are used to attach scientific discourse as metadata.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Borner suggests, in  (Borner, 2006), that in a highly collaborative, network-based and data intensive field, such as Astronomy, interlinking scientific services, documents from the web and expertise  could be used to improve scholarly knowledge and expertise management. In (Borner, 2006), it is proposed that users logging into the system could be assigned an URI and meta-data would be assigned automatically to their activities. Oberle  (Oberle et al., 2003) shows a framework with formal semantics based on ontology for tracking users’ behaviour on a website. His method claims to be advantageous over Mobasher et al.  (Mobasher et al., 2000) (Mobasher, 2001), and Berendt and Spiliopoulou (Berendt et al., 2000) (Berendt, 2002) , as it ensures that it retains full information on each user request and claims to be more suitable for dynamically generated web pages, such as those in a Virtual Observatory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Targeting interesting links to validate users could help to improve the user experience on knowledge discovery and changing the way users employ the Virtual Observatory. In (André et al., 2009), it is claimed that semantic targeting would increase serendipitous knowledge discovery rather than reducing it. Berendt suggests  (Berendt et al., 2002) that semantic web usage mining can for instance be performed on log files that register the user’s behaviour in terms of ontology. These log files can then be mined, for example, to cluster users who view/fetch ontologically related events/observations/data-sets from a different instrument and targeted to users who fetch/view ontologically related events.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Currently, upon logging into the Virtual Observatory users need to know which data object they wish to fetch, which algorithm they will use to process it and which graph engine to display it. By semantically targeting interesting links from other users performing these activities, one could be exposed to the more pertinent algorithms used on the data object of their interest, the different available engines to display this object, which users have fetched data objects ontologically related to the data period at hand and what work have they developed on these data objects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A similar approach to the one proposed here is used in Stellaris  (Hogqvist &amp;amp; Reinefeld, 2007). Stellaris is metadata service that enables users to share resources such as robotic telescopes. Moreover, this research would contribute to the vision of the Virtual Observatory posed by Williams  (Williams et al., 2003), in which peer-reviewed publications that explain well enough what the data means are attached to the data as metadata.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;methodology&quot;&gt;Methodology&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will attempt to measure changes of knowledge discovery while increasing the amount of data links by including links made by users. The impact on knowledge discovery might vary if the links created by users connect one or more nodes with different kinds of objects (publications, algorithms, display engines, etc.). Therefore interoperability (intervening variable) of the user-generated links will be an influential factor in the changes in the measurements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a Virtual Observatory users (the subjects of study) are very different (i.e. students, pot-docs, scientists, etc.) and can experience the VxO in different ways. For instance, students might not be able to identify the potential knowledge discovery traits in the provided links. On the other hand experienced researchers might find the same links obvious and unnecessary. In addition, designing treatments for experienced scientist or post-docs in order to prompt knowledge discovery would be a massively complicated task. Therefore, I propose to have two experiments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, a Pre-test Post-test controlled trial strategy. Using this method will allow us to control differences in the groups. Moreover, it will help us to define concise treatments for the experiment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The subjects will be undergraduate/graduate students of Solar Physics. Students in each treatment will be classified according to their level of knowledge. The product will consist in exercises to be carried out using the HELIO Portal. Subjects will be asked to conduct the knowledge discovery activities using the product.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Treatment 1 will be considered as control group and the subjects will conduct an exercise using the HELIO portal without the Social Facet. In treatment 2, the subjects will receive the same exercise content as in treatment 1 but will be allowed to use Social Facet of HELIO.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second experiment will consist of a Post-test-only randomized controlled trial. As the HELIO portal is accessible online from anywhere in the world, we could use a varied range of users (randomized trial). This time, the treatment will not include exercises. The users will have the chance of using the system in a more natural way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We will take advantage of the activity logging capabilities of the system to collect data. At the same time interviews will be a good way to capture users’ reactions to the tool and also to find out whether the objects they discover with the tool helped them with their research.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second experiment would also give us the opportunity to measure log data sharing frequency between users. This variable can contribute significantly to enable Collective Intelligence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A recent study (Piwowar &amp;amp; Chapman, 2010), discusses several variables that can contribute to data sharing between scientists. The study found an association between ‘author experience’ and data sharing frequency that could be encouraging for our project. Still, it would be needed to explore whether these associations are applicable to our study in the Virtual Observatory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It would be particularly interesting to find relationships between the types of links the users found useful and the user demographic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to enrich the metadata database and to add practical scientific value on the system, data-related publications and algorithms will be notated into the system.
Timeline&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a list of six milestones to complete this project. First, a longitudinal literature survey will have to be carried out during the first six months and will involve identifying and reviewing literature on other socially-driven research portals, semantic web services development, privacy concerns, semantic targeting, semantic advertising and most importantly the HELIO architecture and ontology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will then focus on the design, development and testing of the ontology needed to support the system. I am aiming to re-use other ontologies instead of developing a new one. This is expected to be an iterative activity, with an average duration of four months.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Seven months will then be assigned to design, develop and test the framework to interact with the ontology involved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thereafter, I will need to identify and collect suitable data for the analysis. There will be the need to focus on a specific segment of Heliophysics in which current research is flourishing and is accessible so we can supply the database with all the connections needed. Four moths will be allowed for this objective.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Following the above, the evaluation stage will take place and will last six months. Finally, four months will be allocated for writing up the thesis report.
Works Cited&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;bibliography&quot;&gt;Bibliography&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Williams, R., 2004. Virtual Observatory Architecture Overview. [Online] Available at: http://www.ivoa.net/Documents/Notes/IVOArch/IVOArch-20040615.html [Accessed February 2011].&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Williams, R., Moore, &amp;amp; Hanisch, , 2003. A Virtual Observatory Vision based on Published and Virtual Data. Caltech CACR.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;André, P., Teevan, J. &amp;amp; Dumais, S.T., 2009. From X-Rays to Silly Putty via Uranus: Serendipity and its Role in Web Search. In 27th international conference on Human factors in computing systems. Boston, 2009.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;AstroGrid Team, 2001. The Virtual Observatory Concept. [Online] Available at: http://www.astrogrid.org/wiki/Home/AboutTheVO [Accessed April 2011].&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Bentley, B., 2009. Building a Virtual Observatory for Heliophysics. EARTH, MOON, AND PLANETS, 104(1-4), pp.87-91. International Heliophysical Year 2007: Second European General Assembly, Italy&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Third UN/ESA/NASA Workshop, Japan.&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Berendt, B., 2002. Using site semantics to analyze, visualize and support navigation. Data Mining and Knowledge Discovery. DATA MINING AND KNOWLEDGE DISCOVERY, 6(1), pp.37-59.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Berendt, B., Hotho, &amp;amp; Stumme, , 2002. Towards Semantic Web Minning. THE SEMANTIC WEB — ISWC 2002, 2342, pp.264-278.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Berendt, B., Spiliopoulou, &amp;amp; Sprin, , 2000. Analysing navigation behaviour in web sites integrating multiple information systems. THE VLDB JOURNAL, 9(1), pp.56-75.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Borne, K., 2003. Distributed Data Mining in the National Virtual Observatory. In Data Mining and Knowledge Discovery: Theory, Tools, and Technology V. Orlando, 2003. Proc. SPIE.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Borner, K., 2006. Semantic Association Networking using Semantic Web Technology to improve scholarly knowledge and expertise management. In Geroimenko, V. Visualizing the Semantic Web XML-Based Internet and Information Visualization. Springer-Verlag. pp.183-98.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Brescia, M. et al., 2010. DAME: a Web Oriented Infrastructure for Scientific Data Mining &amp;amp; Exploration. Instrumentation and Methods for Astrophysics (astro-ph.IM).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ciccarese, P. et al., 2008. The SWAN Biomedical Discourse Ontology. Biomed Informatics, (41), pp.739-51.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Das, S. et al., 2009. Building Biomedical Web Communities Using A Semantically-Aware Content Management System. Briefings in Bioinformatics, 10, pp.129-38.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Djorgovski, G. &amp;amp; Williams, R., 2005. Virtual Observatory: From Concept to Implementation. From Clark Lake to the Long Wavelength Array: Bill Erickson’s Radio Science ASP Conference Series, 345, p.517.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fox, P. et al., 2007. Semantic Web Services for Interdisciplinary Scientific Data Query and Retrieval. In Proceedings of the Semantic eScience Workshop co-located with the Association for the Advancement of Artificial Intelligence Conference., 2007. AAAI.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fox, P. et al., 2009. Ontology-supported scientific data frameworks: The virtual solar-terrestrial observatory experience. Computers &amp;amp; Geosciences, 35(4), pp.724-38.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fox, P. et al., 2007. The VIRTUAL SOLAR-TERRESTRIAL OBSERVATORY: interdisciplinary data-driven science. In IAU XXVI General Assembly., 2007. Highlights of Astronomy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Genot, V. et al., 2010. Space Weather Application AMDA. Advances in Space Research, 45(9), pp.1145-55.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hogqvist, M. &amp;amp; Reinefeld, A., 2007. Stellaris: An RDF-based Information Service for AstroGrid-D. In German e-Science conference., 2007.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lawrence, A., 2002. AstroGrid : powering the Virtual Observatory. Proceedings of SPIE, 4846, pp.6-12.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Longo, G., 2011. IVOA Knowledge Discovery in Databases. [Online] Available at: http://www.ivoa.net/cgi-bin/twiki/bin/view/IVOA/IvoaKDD [Accessed May 2011].&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;NASA, 2011. Heliophysics. [Online] Available at: http://science.nasa.gov/heliophysics/ [Accessed May 2011].&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Martens, P., 2010. Heliophysics Data Environment: What’s next? In American Geophysical Union Fall Meeting., 2010.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mobasher, B., 2001. Using ontologies to discover domain-level web usage proﬁles. In 2nd Workshop on Semantic Web Mining., 2001.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mobasher, B., Luo, T., Dai, H. &amp;amp; Sun, Y., 2000. Integrating web usage and content mining for more effective personalization. Lecture Notes in Computer Science, 1875, pp.165-76.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oberle, D., Berendt, B., Hotho, A. &amp;amp; Gonzalez, J., 2003. Conceptual User Tracking. In Proc. of the Atlantic Web Intelligence Conference., 2003.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Quin, P., 2003. EUROPEAN VIRTUAL OBSERVATORY. [Online] Available at: reuna.cl [Accessed March 2011].&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Piwowar , H. &amp;amp; Chapman, W.W., 2010. Public sharing of research datasets: A pilot study of associations. Journal of Informetrics, 4(2), pp.148-56.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Roure, D.C.D., 2008. The New e-Science. [Online] IEEE Available at: http://www.slideshare.net/dder/the-new-science-bangalore-edition [Accessed January 2011].&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Creative Commons License
This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivs 3.0 Unported License.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;The Heliophysics Integrated Observatory is a new European e-Infrastructure funded by the 7th framework program. The program started in June 2009, and will last 36 months. It addresses the needs of scientists of understanding, modeling and predicting the inﬂuence of solar activity on the solar system as a whole. Bob Bentley from the Mullard Space Science Laboratory leads HELIO. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 10 Oct 2011 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://kjgarza.github.io/pages/2011/10/10/research-proposal.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://kjgarza.github.io/pages/2011/10/10/research-proposal.html</guid>
        
        <category>phd proposal</category>
        
        <category>scientific collaboration</category>
        
        
        <category>pages</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
